<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article>
  <preamble>mikheev J02-3002.pdf</preamble>
  <titre>Periods, Capitalized Words, etc.</titre>
  <auteurs>
    <auteur>
      <name>Andrei Mikheev∗</name>
      <mail>mikheev@cogsci.ed.ac.uk</mail>
    </auteur>
  </auteurs>
  <abstract>Proper names are the main concern of the named-entity recognition subtask (Chinchor 1998) of information extraction. The main objective of this subtask is the identification of proper names and also their classification into semantic categories (person, organization, location, etc.).1 There the disambiguation of the first word in a sentence (and in other ambiguous positions) is one of the central problems: about 20% of named entities occur in ambiguous positions. For instance, the word Black in the sentenceinitial position can stand for a person’s surname but can also refer to the color. Even in multiword capitalized phrases, the first word can belong to the rest of the phrase or can be just an external modifier. In the sentence Daily, Mason and Partners lost their court case, it is clear that Daily, Mason and Partners is the name of a company. In the sentence Unfortunately, Mason and Partners lost their court case, the name of the company does not include the word Unfortunately, but the word Daily is just as common a word as Unfortunately. Identification of proper names is also important in machine translation, because usually proper names are transliterated (i.e., phonetically translated) rather than properly (semantically) translated. In confidential texts, such as medical records, proper names must be identified and removed before making such texts available to people unauthorized to have access to personally identifiable information. And in general, most tasks that involve text analysis will benefit from the robust disambiguation of capitalized words into proper names and common words. Another important task of text normalization is sentence boundary disambiguation (SBD) or sentence splitting. Segmenting text into sentences is an important aspect in developing many applications: syntactic parsing, information extraction, machine translation, question answering, text alignment, document summarization, etc. Sentence splitting in most cases is a simple matter: a period, an exclamation mark, or a question mark usually signals a sentence boundary. In certain cases, however, a period denotes a decimal point or is a part of an abbreviation, and thus it does not necessarily signal a sentence boundary. Furthermore, an abbreviation itself can be the last token in a sentence in which case its period acts at the same time as part of this abbreviation and as the end-of-sentence indicator (fullstop). A detailed introduction to the SBD problem can be found in Palmer and Hearst (1997). The disambiguation of capitalized words and sentence boundaries presents a chicken-and-egg problem. If we know that a capitalized word that follows a period is a common word, we can safely assign such period as sentence terminal. On the other hand, if we know that a period is not sentence terminal, then we can conclude that the following capitalized word is a proper name. Another frequent source of ambiguity in end-of-sentence marking is introduced by abbreviations: if we know that the word that precedes a period is not an abbreviation, then almost certainly this period denotes a sentence boundary. If, however, this word is an abbreviation, then it is not that easy to make a clear decision. This problem is exacerbated by the fact that abbreviations do not form a closed set; that is, one cannot list all possible abbreviations. Moreover, abbreviations can coincide with regular words; for example, “in” can denote an abbreviation for “inches,” “no” can denote an abbreviation for “number,” and “bus” can denote an abbreviation for “business.” In this article we present a method that tackles sentence boundaries, capitalized words, and abbreviations in a uniform way through a document-centered approach. As opposed to the two dominant techniques of computing statistics about the words that surround potential sentence boundaries or writing specialized grammars, our ap-</abstract>
  <biblio>Washington, D.C., Morgan Kaufmann. Brill, Eric. 1995a. Transformation-based error-driven learning and natural language parsing: A case study in part-of-speech tagging. Computational Linguistics 21(4):543–565. Brill, Eric. 1995b. “Unsupervised learning of disambiguation rules for part of speech tagging.” In David Yarovsky and Kenneth Church, editors, Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Very Large Corpora, pages 1–13, Somerset, New Jersey. Association for Computational Linguistics. Burnage, Gavin. 1990. CELEX: A Guide for Users. Centre for Lexical Information, Nijmegen, Netherlands.
Francis, W. Nelson and Henry Kucera. 1982. Frequency Analysis of English Usage: Lexicon and Grammar. Houghton Mifflin, New York. Gale, William, Kenneth Church, and David Yarowsky. 1992. “One sense per discourse.” In Proceedings of the Fourth DARPA Speech and Natural Language Workshop, pages 233–237. Grefenstette, Gregory and Pasi Tapanainen. 1994. “What is a word, what is a sentence? Problems of tokenization.” In The Proceedings of Third Conference on Computational Lexicography and Text Research (COMPLEX’94), Budapest, Hungary. Krupka, George R. and Kevin Hausman. 1998. Isoquest Inc.: Description of the netowl extractor system as used for MUC-7. In Proceedings of the Seventh Message Understanding Conference (MUC-7), Fairfax, VA. Morgan Kaufmann. Kuhn, Roland and Renato de Mori. 1998. A cache-based natural language model for speech recognition. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence 12:570–583. Kupiec, Julian. 1992. Robust part-of-speech tagging using a hidden Markov model. Computer Speech and Language. Mani, Inderjeet and T. Richard MacMillan. 1995. “Identifying unknown proper</biblio>
</article>