<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article>
  <preambule>Torres.pdf</preambule>
  <titre>Summary Evaluation with and without References</titre>
  <auteurs>
    <auteur>
      <name>Juan-Manuel Torres-Moreno</name>
      <mail>juan-manuel.torres@univ-avignon.fr</mail>
      <affiliation></affiliation>
    </auteur>
    <auteur>
      <name>Horacio Saggion</name>
      <mail>horacio.saggion@upf.edu</mail>
      <affiliation></affiliation>
    </auteur>
    <auteur>
      <name>Iria da Cunha</name>
      <mail>iria.dacunha@upf.edu</mail>
      <affiliation></affiliation>
    </auteur>
    <auteur>
      <name>Eric SanJuan</name>
      <mail>eric.sanjuan@univ-avignon.fr</mail>
      <affiliation></affiliation>
    </auteur>
    <auteur>
      <name>Patricia Velázquez-Morales</name>
      <mail></mail>
      <affiliation></affiliation>
    </auteur>
  </auteurs>
  <abstract>We study a new content-based method for the evaluation of text summarization systems without human models which is used to produce system rankings. The research is carried out using a new content-based evaluation framework called FRESA to compute a variety of divergences among probability distributions. We apply our comparison framework to various well-established content-based evaluation measures in text summarization such as COVERAGE, RESPONSIVENESS, PYRAMIDS and ROUGE studying their associations in various text summarization tasks including generic multi-document summarization in English and French, focus-based multi-document summarization in English and generic single-document summarization in French and Spanish.</abstract>
  <introduction>T
EXT summarization evaluation has always been a
complex
and
controversial
issue
in
computational
linguistics. In the last decade, signiﬁcant advances have been
made in this ﬁeld as well as various evaluation measures have
been designed. Two evaluation campaigns have been led by
the U.S. agence DARPA. The ﬁrst one, SUMMAC, ran from
1996 to 1998 under the auspices of the Tipster program [1],
and the second one, entitled DUC (Document Understanding
Conference) [2], was the main evaluation forum from 2000
until 2007. Nowadays, the Text Analysis Conference (TAC)
[3] provides a forum for assessment of different information
access technologies including text summarization.
Evaluation in text summarization can be extrinsic or
intrinsic [4]. In an extrinsic evaluation, the summaries are
assessed in the context of an speciﬁc task carried out by a
human or a machine. In an intrinsic evaluation, the summaries
are evaluated in reference to some ideal model. SUMMAC
was mainly extrinsic while DUC and TAC followed an
intrinsic evaluation paradigm. In an intrinsic evaluation, an
Manuscript received June 8, 2010. Manuscript accepted for publication July
25, 2010.
Juan-Manuel
Torres-Moreno
is
with
LIA/Université
d’Avignon,
France
and
École
Polytechnique
de
Montréal,
Canada
(juan-manuel.torres@univ-avignon.fr).
Eric
SanJuan
is
with
LIA/Université
d’Avignon,
France
(eric.sanjuan@univ-avignon.fr).
Horacio
Saggion
is
with
DTIC/Universitat
Pompeu
Fabra,
Spain
(horacio.saggion@upf.edu).
Iria
da
Cunha
is
with
IULA/Universitat
Pompeu
Fabra,
Spain;
LIA/Université d’Avignon, France and Instituto de Ingenier´ıa/UNAM, Mexico
(iria.dacunha@upf.edu).
Patricia
Velázquez-Morales
is
with
VM
Labs,
France
(patricia velazquez@yahoo.com).
automatically generated summary (peer) has to be compared
with one or more reference summaries (models). DUC used
an interface called SEE to allow human judges to compare
a peer with a model. Thus, judges give a COVERAGE score
to each peer produced by a system and the ﬁnal system
COVERAGE score is the average of the COVERAGE’s scores
asigned. These system’s COVERAGE scores can then be used
to rank summarization systems. In the case of query-focused
summarization (e.g. when the summary should answer a
question or series of questions) a RESPONSIVENESS score
is also assigned to each summary, which indicates how
responsive the summary is to the question(s).
Because manual comparison of peer summaries with model
summaries is an arduous and costly process, a body of
research has been produced in the last decade on automatic
content-based evaluation procedures. Early studies used text
similarity measures such as cosine similarity (with or without
weighting schema) to compare peer and model summaries
[5]. Various vocabulary overlap measures such as n-grams
overlap or longest common subsequence between peer and
model have also been proposed [6], [7]. The BLEU machine
translation evaluation measure [8] has also been tested in
summarization [9]. The DUC conferences adopted the ROUGE
package for content-based evaluation [10]. ROUGE implements
a series of recall measures based on n-gram co-occurrence
between a peer summary and a set of model summaries. These
measures are used to produce systems’ rank. It has been shown
that system rankings, produced by some ROUGE measures
(e.g., ROUGE-2, which uses 2-grams), have a correlation with
rankings produced using COVERAGE.
In recent years the PYRAMIDS evaluation method [11] has
been introduced. It is based on the distribution of “content”
of a set of model summaries. Summary Content Units (SCUs)
are ﬁrst identiﬁed in the model summaries, then each SCU
receives a weight which is the number of models containing
or expressing the same unit. Peer SCUs are identiﬁed in the
peer, matched against model SCUs, and weighted accordingly.
The PYRAMIDS score given to a peer is the ratio of the sum
of the weights of its units and the sum of the weights of the
best possible ideal summary with the same number of SCUs as
the peer. The PYRAMIDS scores can be also used for ranking
summarization systems. [11] showed that PYRAMIDS scores
produced reliable system rankings when multiple (4 or more)
models were used and that PYRAMIDS rankings correlate with
rankings produced by ROUGE-2 and ROUGE-SU2 (i.e. ROUGE
with skip 2-grams). However, this method requires the creation</introduction>
  <corps>13
Polibits (42) 2010

of models and the identiﬁcation, matching, and weighting of
SCUs in both: models and peers.

while other measures compare peers with all or some of the
input material:
MEASUREM(SUMi,k, I′
i)
(4)
where I′
i is some subset of input Ii. The values produced
by the measures for each summary SUMi,k are averaged
for each system k = 0, . . . , s −1 and these averages are
used to produce a ranking. Rankings are then compared
using Spearman Rank correlation [17] which is used to
measure the degree of association between two variables
whose values are used to rank objects. We have chosen
to use this correlation to compare directly results to those
presented in [12]. Computation of correlations is done using
the Statistics-RankCorrelation-0.12 package1, which computes
the rank correlation between two vectors. We also veriﬁed
the good conformity of the results with the correlation test
of Kendall τ calculated with the statistical software R. The
two nonparametric tests of Spearman and Kendall do not
really stand out as the treatment of ex-æquo. The good
correspondence between the two tests shows that they do not
introduce bias in our analysis. Subsequently will mention only
the ρ of Sperman more widely used in this ﬁeld.
A. Tools
We carry out experimentation using a new summarization
evaluation framework: FRESA –FRamework for Evaluating
Summaries Automatically–, which includes document-based
summary
evaluation
measures
based
on
probabilities
distribution2. As in the ROUGE package, FRESA supports
different n-grams and skip n-grams probability distributions.
The FRESA environment can be used in the evaluation of
summaries in English, French, Spanish and Catalan, and it
integrates ﬁltering and lemmatization in the treatment of
summaries and documents. It is developed in Perl and will
be made publicly available. We also use the ROUGE package

– J S summarizer, a summarization system that scores
and ranks sentences according to their Jensen-Shannon
divergence to the source document;
– a lead-based summarization system that selects the lead
sentences of the document;
– a
random-based
summarization
system
that
selects
sentences at random;
– Open Text Summarizer [23], a multi-lingual summarizer
based on the frequency and
– commercial systems: Word, SSSummarizer8, Pertinence9
and Copernic10.
C. Evaluation Measures
The following measures derived from human assessment of
the content of the summaries are used in our experiments:
– COVERAGE is understood as the degree to which one
peer summary conveys the same information as a model
summary [2]. COVERAGE was used in DUC evaluations.
This measure is used as indicated in equation 3 using
human references or models.
– RESPONSIVENESS ranks summaries in a 5-point scale
indicating how well the summary satisﬁed a given
information need [2]. It is used in focused-based
summarization tasks. This measure is used as indicated
in equation 4 since a human judges the summary
with respect to a given input “user need” (e.g., a
question). RESPONSIVENESS was used in DUC and TAC
evaluations.
– PYRAMIDS [11] is a content assessment measure which
compares content units in a peer summary to weighted
content units in a set of model summaries. This
measure is used as indicated in equation 3 using human
references or models. PYRAMIDS is the adopted metric
for content-based evaluation in the TAC evaluations.
For DUC and TAC datasets the values of these measures are
available and we used them directly. We used the following
automatic evaluation measures in our experiments:
– ROUGE [14], which is a recall metric that takes into
account n-grams as units of content for comparing peer
and model summaries. The ROUGE formula speciﬁed in

TABLE I
SPEARMAN CORRELATION OF CONTENT-BASED MEASURES IN TAC’08
UPDATE SUMMARIZATION TASK
Mesure
PYRAMIDS
p-value
RESPONSIVENESS
p-value
ROUGE-2
0.96
p &lt; 0.005
0.92
p &lt; 0.005
J S
0.85
p &lt; 0.005
0.74
p &lt; 0.005
multi-document summarization in Spanish and French. In spite
of the fact that the experiments for French and Spanish corpora
use less data points (i.e., less summarizers per task) than
for English, results are still quite signiﬁcant. For DUC’04,
we computed the J S measure for each peer summary in
tasks 2 and 5 and we used J S, ROUGE, COVERAGE and
RESPONSIVENESS scores to produce systems’ rankings. The
various Spearman’s rank correlation values for DUC’04 are
presented in Tables II (for task 2) and III (for task 5).
For task 2, we have veriﬁed a strong correlation between
J S and COVERAGE. For task 5, the correlation between
J S and COVERAGE is weak, and that between J S and
RESPONSIVENESS is weak and negative.
Although the Opinion Summarization (OS) task is a new
type of summarization task and its evaluation is a complicated
issue, we have decided to compare J S rankings with those
obtained using PYRAMIDS and RESPONSIVENESS in TAC’08.
Spearman’s correlation values are listed in Table IV. As it can
be seen, there is weak and negative correlation of J S with
both PYRAMIDS and RESPONSIVENESS. Correlation between
PYRAMIDS and RESPONSIVENESS rankings is high for this
task (0.71 Spearman’s correlation value).
For experimentation in mono-document summarization
in Spanish and French, we have run 11 multi-lingual
summarization systems; for experimentation in French, we
have run 12 systems. In both cases, we have produced
summaries at a compression rate close to the compression rate
of the authors’ provided abstracts. We have then computed J S
and ROUGE measures for each summary and we have averaged
the measure’s values for each system. These averages were
used to produce rankings per each measure. We computed
Spearman’s correlations for all pairs of rankings.
Results are presented in Tables V, VI and VII. All results
show medium to strong correlation between the J S measures
and ROUGE measures. However the J S measure based on
uni-grams has lower correlation than J Ss which use n-grams
of higher order. Note that table VII presents results for
generic multi-document summarization in French, in this
case correlation scores are lower than correlation scores for
single-document summarization in French, a result which may
be expected given the diversity of input in multi-document
summarization.</corps>
  <conclusion>This paper has presented a series of experiments in
content-based measures that do not rely on the use of model
summaries for comparison purposes. We have carried out
extensive experimentation with different summarization tasks
drawing a clearer picture of tasks where the measures could
be applied. This paper makes the following contributions:
– We have shown that if we are only interested in ranking
summarization systems according to the content of their
automatic summaries, there are tasks were models could
be subtituted by the full document in the computation of
the J S measure obtaining reliable rankings. However,
we have also found that the substitution of models
by full-documents is not always advisable. We have
Summary Evaluation with and without References
17
Polibits (42) 2010

TABLE II
SPEARMAN ρ OF CONTENT-BASED MEASURES WITH COVERAGE IN DUC’04 TASK 2
Mesure
COVERAGE
p-value
ROUGE-2
0.79
p &lt; 0.0050
J S
0.68
p &lt; 0.0025
TABLE III
SPEARMAN ρ OF CONTENT-BASED MEASURES IN DUC’04 TASK 5
Mesure
COVERAGE
p-value
RESPONSIVENESS
p-value
ROUGE-2
0.78
p &lt; 0.001
0.44
p &lt; 0.05
J S
0.40
p &lt; 0.050
-0.18
p &lt; 0.25
TABLE IV
SPEARMAN ρ OF CONTENT-BASED MEASURES IN TAC’08 OS TASK
Mesure
PYRAMIDS
p-value
RESPONSIVENESS
p-value
J S
-0.13
p &lt; 0.25
-0.14
p &lt; 0.25
TABLE V
SPEARMAN ρ OF CONTENT-BASED MEASURES WITH ROUGE IN THE Medicina Cl´ınica CORPUS (SPANISH)
Mesure
ROUGE-1
p-value
ROUGE-2
p-value
ROUGE-SU4
p-value
J S
0.56
p &lt; 0.100
0.46
p &lt; 0.100
0.45
p &lt; 0.200
J S2
0.88
p &lt; 0.001
0.80
p &lt; 0.002
0.81
p &lt; 0.005
J S4
0.88
p &lt; 0.001
0.80
p &lt; 0.002
0.81
p &lt; 0.005
J SM
0.82
p &lt; 0.005
0.71
p &lt; 0.020
0.71
p &lt; 0.010
found weak correlation among different rankings in
complex summarization tasks such as the summarization
of biographical information and the summarization of
opinions.
– We have also carried out large-scale experiments in
Spanish and French which show positive medium to
strong correlation among system’s ranks produced by
ROUGE and divergence measures that do not use the
model summaries.
– We have also presented a new framework, FRESA, for
the computation of measures based on J S divergence.
Following the ROUGE approach, FRESA package use
word uni-grams, 2-grams and skip n-grams computing
divergences. This framework will be available to the
community for research purposes.
Although we have made a number of contributions, this paper
leaves many open questions than need to be addressed. In
order to verify correlation between ROUGE and J S, in the
short term we intend to extend our investigation to other
languages such as Portuguese and Chinesse for which we
have access to data and summarization technology. We also
plan to apply FRESA to the rest of the DUC and TAC
summarization tasks, by using several smoothing techniques.
As a novel idea, we contemplate the possibility of adapting
the evaluation framework for the phrase compression task

TABLE VI
SPEARMAN ρ OF CONTENT-BASED MEASURES WITH ROUGE IN THE PISTES CORPUS (FRENCH)
Mesure
ROUGE-1
p-value
ROUGE-2
p-value
ROUGE-SU4
p-value
J S
0.70
p &lt; 0.050
0.73
p &lt; 0.05
0.73
p &lt; 0.500
J S2
0.93
p &lt; 0.002
0.86
p &lt; 0.01
0.86
p &lt; 0.005
J S4
0.83
p &lt; 0.020
0.76
p &lt; 0.05
0.76
p &lt; 0.050
J SM
0.88
p &lt; 0.010
0.83
p &lt; 0.02
0.83
p &lt; 0.010
TABLE VII
SPEARMAN ρ OF CONTENT-BASED MEASURES WITH ROUGE IN THE RPM2 CORPUS (FRENCH)
Measure
ROUGE-1
p-value
ROUGE-2
p-value
ROUGE-SU4
p-value
J S
0.830
p &lt; 0.002
0.660
p &lt; 0.05
0.741
p &lt; 0.01
J S2
0.800
p &lt; 0.005
0.590
p &lt; 0.05
0.680
p &lt; 0.02
J S4
0.750
p &lt; 0.010
0.520
p &lt; 0.10
0.620
p &lt; 0.05
J SM
0.850
p &lt; 0.002
0.640
p &lt; 0.05
0.740
p &lt; 0.01</conclusion>
  <discussion>The departing point for our inquiry into text summarization
evaluation has been recent work on the use of content-based
evaluation metrics that do not rely on human models but that
compare summary content to input content directly [12]. We
have some positive and some negative results regarding the
direct use of the full document in content-based evaluation.
We have veriﬁed that in both generic muti-document
summarization
and
in
topic-based
multi-document
summarization
in
English
correlation
among
measures
that use human models (PYRAMIDS,
RESPONSIVENESS
and ROUGE) and a measure that does not use models
(J S divergence) is strong. We have found that correlation
among the same measures is weak for summarization of
biographical information and summarization of opinions in
blogs. We believe that in these cases content-based measures
should be considered, in addition to the input document, the
summarization task (i.e. text-based representation, description)
to better assess the content of the peers [25], the task being a
determinant factor in the selection of content for the summary.
Our multi-lingual experiments in generic single-document
summarization
conﬁrm
a
strong
correlation
among
the
J S divergence and ROUGE measures. It is worth noting
that
ROUGE
is
in
general
the
chosen
framework
for
presenting content-based evaluation results in non-English
summarization.
For the experiments in Spanish, we are conscious that we
only have one model summary to compare with the peers.
Nevertheless, these models are the corresponding abstracts
written by the authors. As the experiments in [26] show, the
professionals of a specialized domain (as, for example, the
medical domain) adopt similar strategies to summarize their
texts and they tend to choose roughly the same content chunks
for their summaries. Previous studies have shown that author
abstracts are able to reformulate content with ﬁdelity [27] and
these abstracts are ideal candidates for comparison purposes.
Because of this, the summary of the author of a medical article
can be taken as reference for summaries evaluation. It is worth
noting that there is still debate on the number of models to be
used in summarization evaluation [28]. In the French corpus
PISTES, we suspect the situation is similar to the Spanish
case.</discussion>
  <biblio>[1] I.
Mani,
G.
Klein,
D.
House,
L.
Hirschman,
T.
Firmin,
and
B. Sundheim, “Summac: a text summarization evaluation,” Natural
Language Engineering, vol. 8, no. 1, pp. 43–68, 2002.
[2] P. Over, H. Dang, and D. Harman, “DUC in context,” IPM, vol. 43,
no. 6, pp. 1506–1520, 2007.
[3] Proceedings of the Text Analysis Conference.
Gaithesburg, Maryland,
USA: NIST, November 17-19 2008.
[4] K. Sp¨arck Jones and J. Galliers, Evaluating Natural Language
Processing Systems, An Analysis and Review, ser. Lecture Notes in
Computer Science.
Springer, 1996, vol. 1083.
[5] R. L. Donaway, K. W. Drummey, and L. A. Mather, “A comparison of
rankings produced by summarization evaluation measures,” in NAACL
Workshop on Automatic Summarization, 2000, pp. 69–78.
[6] H. Saggion, D. Radev, S. Teufel, and W. Lam, “Meta-evaluation
of Summaries in a Cross-lingual Environment using Content-based
Metrics,” in COLING 2002, Taipei, Taiwan, August 2002, pp. 849–855.
[7] D. R. Radev, S. Teufel, H. Saggion, W. Lam, J. Blitzer, H. Qi, A. C¸ elebi,
D. Liu, and E. Drábek, “Evaluation challenges in large-scale document
summarization,” in ACL’03, 2003, pp. 375–382.
[8] K. Papineni, S. Roukos, T. Ward, , and W. J. Zhu, “BLEU: a method
for automatic evaluation of machine translation,” in ACL’02, 2002, pp.
311–318.
[9] K. Pastra and H. Saggion, “Colouring summaries BLEU,” in Evaluation
Initiatives in Natural Language Processing. Budapest, Hungary: EACL,
14 April 2003.
[10] C.-Y.
Lin,
“ROUGE:
A
Package
for
Automatic
Evaluation
of
Summaries,” in Text Summarization Branches Out: ACL-04 Workshop,
M.-F. Moens and S. Szpakowicz, Eds., Barcelona, July 2004, pp. 74–81.
[11] A. Nenkova and R. J. Passonneau, “Evaluating Content Selection in
Summarization: The Pyramid Method,” in HLT-NAACL, 2004, pp.
145–152.
[12] A. Louis and A. Nenkova, “Automatically Evaluating Content Selection
in Summarization without Human Models,” in Empirical Methods in
Natural Language Processing, Singapore, August 2009, pp. 306–314.
[Online]. Available: http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/D/D09/D09-1032
[13] J. Lin, “Divergence Measures based on the Shannon Entropy,” IEEE
Transactions on Information Theory, vol. 37, no. 145-151, 1991.
[14] C.-Y. Lin and E. Hovy, “Automatic Evaluation of Summaries Using
N-gram Co-occurrence Statistics,” in HLT-NAACL.
Morristown, NJ,
USA: Association for Computational Linguistics, 2003, pp. 71–78.
[15] C.-Y. Lin, G. Cao, J. Gao, and J.-Y. Nie, “An information-theoretic
approach to automatic evaluation of summaries,” in HLT-NAACL,
Morristown, USA, 2006, pp. 463–470.
[16] S. Kullback and R. Leibler, “On information and sufﬁciency,” Ann. of
Math. Stat., vol. 22, no. 1, pp. 79–86, 1951.
[17] S. Siegel and N. Castellan, Nonparametric Statistics for the Behavioral
Sciences.
McGraw-Hill, 1998.
[18] C. de Loupy, M. Guégan, C. Ayache, S. Seng, and J.-M. Torres-Moreno,
“A
French
Human
Reference
Corpus
for
multi-documents
summarization
and
sentence
compression,”
in
LREC’10,
vol.
2,
Malta, 2010, p. In press.
[19] S. Fernandez, E. SanJuan, and J.-M. Torres-Moreno, “Textual Energy
of Associative Memories: performants applications of Enertex algorithm
in text summarization and topic segmentation,” in MICAI’07, 2007, pp.
861–871.
[20] J.-M.
Torres-Moreno,
P.
Velázquez-Morales,
and
J.-G.
Meunier,
“Condensés de textes par des méthodes numériques,” in JADT’02, vol. 2,
St Malo, France, 2002, pp. 723–734.
[21] J. Vivaldi, I. da Cunha, J.-M. Torres-Moreno, and P. Velázquez-Morales,
“Automatic
summarization
using
terminological
and
semantic
resources,” in LREC’10, vol. 2, Malta, 2010, p. In press.
[22] J.-M. Torres-Moreno and J. Ramirez, “REG : un algorithme glouton
appliqué au résumé automatique de texte,” in JADT’10.
Rome, 2010,
p. In press.
[23] V. Yatsko and T. Vishnyakov, “A method for evaluating modern
systems of automatic text summarization,” Automatic Documentation
and Mathematical Linguistics, vol. 41, no. 3, pp. 93–103, 2007.
[24] C. D. Manning and H. Sch¨utze, Foundations of Statistical Natural
Language Processing.
Cambridge, Massachusetts: The MIT Press,
1999.
[25] K. Sp¨arck Jones, “Automatic summarising: The state of the art,” IPM,
vol. 43, no. 6, pp. 1449–1481, 2007.
[26] I. da Cunha, L. Wanner, and M. T. Cabré, “Summarization of specialized
discourse: The case of medical articles in spanish,” Terminology, vol. 13,
no. 2, pp. 249–286, 2007.
[27] C.-K. Chuah, “Types of lexical substitution in abstracting,” in ACL
Student Research Workshop.
Toulouse, France: Association for
Computational Linguistics, 9-11 July 2001 2001, pp. 49–54.
[28] K. Owkzarzak and H. T. Dang, “Evaluation of automatic summaries:
Metrics under varying data conditions,” in UCNLG+Sum’09, Suntec,
Singapore, August 2009, pp. 23–30.
[29] K. Knight and D. Marcu, “Statistics-based summarization-step one:
Sentence compression,” in Proceedings of the National Conference on
Artiﬁcial Intelligence.
Menlo Park, CA; Cambridge, MA; London;
AAAI Press; MIT Press; 1999, 2000, pp. 703–710.
Summary Evaluation with and without References
19
Polibits (42) 2010</biblio>
</article>